<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Flat priors</title>
    <description>Musings on pharmacometrics &amp; clinical pharmacology, statistics, drug development, software engineering, innovation, and other random topics</description>
    <link>http://ronkeizer.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ronkeizer.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Best books of 2014</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ronkeizer.github.io//assets/books.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;books&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Bill Gates shared his list of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gatesnotes.com/About-Bill-Gates/Best-Books-2014&quot;&gt;best books of 2014&lt;/a&gt;, which stimulated me to think about the best books I read this year. Unfortunately, recent fatherhood has kept me away from a lot of books I planned to read this year, but I did manage to squeeze in a couple of very interesting ones. These are my 5-star books from 2014:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The boys in the Boat&lt;/strong&gt; (Daniel James Brown): very powerful narrative about the 1936 US Olympic rowing team, a collection of working-class students from the Washington state that conquered the world in Nazi-Germany.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Countdown to zero day&lt;/strong&gt; (Kim Zetter): The thrilling tale of the the Stuxnet virus, the first (known) cyberwarfare weapon that took down an Iranian nuclear plant. It also explains why we should be much more vigilant about securing our public utilities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cool Gray City of Love&lt;/strong&gt; (Gary Kamiya): An engaging book about San Francisco’s short but exciting history. In 49 short stories the author visits places in and around SF to tell their history.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zero to One&lt;/strong&gt;: About technological advance, entrepeneurship, and how the world works in general. Peter Thiel’s book transcends most other books written by Silicon Valley VCs (like &lt;strong&gt;The Hard Thing about Hard Things&lt;/strong&gt; from Ben Horowitz, also released this year and an interesting read) due to its more philosophic nature. The book is short, so I plan to re-read it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disappointments&quot;&gt;Disappointments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I was looking forward a lot to the release of &lt;strong&gt;the Bone Clocks&lt;/strong&gt;, the new book by David Mitchell (author of Cloud Atlas). I’m sad to say it disappointed me a lot. Althought the narrative and dialogue was strong as ever, the story really fell apart somewhere in Chapter 5 where it got lost in some holistic science-fiction mumbo-jumbo. A pity, because Cloud Atlas was awesome…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A book by another favorite author disappointed me too: &lt;strong&gt;the Circle&lt;/strong&gt;, by David Eggers is written around a very relevant theme and promised to be the &lt;strong&gt;1984&lt;/strong&gt; of our generation. Although it did stir up much-needed discussions about online privacy, I think it stretched beyond belief Silicon Valley’s tendency to disregard privacy and glorify technological advance. Not a bad read overall, but over-the-top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please drop any suggestions you have in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 13:40:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://ronkeizer.github.io//books/2014/12/10/best-books-2014/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ronkeizer.github.io//books/2014/12/10/best-books-2014/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Upgrading NONMEM to Yosemite</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Apple released their new OS (Yosemite) a few weeks ago. Unfortunately upgrading to the new system breaks the installation of NONMEM, PsN, and Pirana. Here’s what I did to get up and running again. Altogether this should take less than 20 minutes. &lt;em&gt;Please note that I cannot be held liable for any damage caused directly or indirectly by following the advice below!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 1&lt;/strong&gt;: You need to re-install gcc/gfortran. You can install from source, or from e.g. HomeBrew, but I just chose to take the binaries from &lt;a href=&quot;http://hpc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; which had just updated their versions. Download gcc and gfortran for Yosemite. Then in the console run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/Downloads
sudo tar -xvf gcc-5.0-bin.tar -C / 
sudo tar -xvf gfortran-5.0-bin.tar -C /&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Re-install the Apple developer tools for Yosemite. &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/downloads/index.action#&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt; and install the ones for OSX 10.10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 3&lt;/strong&gt;: Now you are ready to re-install NONMEM. I used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /Users/ronkeizer/Dropbox/Software/NONMEM/nm730CD_essential
sudo /bin/bash SETUP73 /Users/ronkeizer/Dropbox/Software/NONMEM/nm730CD_essential /opt/NONMEM/nm73g gfortran y ar same rec i&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(But change the source and target folders to your own of course!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 4&lt;/strong&gt;: Don’t forget to update psn.conf if you installed to a new location. Use e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;sudo nano /Library/Perl/5.16/PsN_4_2_0/psn.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to edit the system-wide configuration file or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;nano ~/psn.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if you have a personal psn.conf file. Also, you might need to re-install some Perl modules for PsN:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;sudo cpan -i Math::Random
sudo cpan -i Statistics::Distributions&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 5&lt;/strong&gt;: To make Pirana work again, the only thing you need to do is re-install XQuartz, download &lt;a href=&quot;http://xquartz.macosforge.org/landing/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all, folks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 11:49:34 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://ronkeizer.github.io//nonmem/update/2014/11/05/upgrading-to-yosemite/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ronkeizer.github.io//nonmem/update/2014/11/05/upgrading-to-yosemite/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
